all right welcome back to cohort
Andrew take
away really quickly can you all hear me
okay perfect um yeah so hey everyone
welcome back uh cohort 6 just resuming
here Midway through July uh we're going
to be starting the second half of the
textbook uh first half we were
introduced to a lot of the underlying
ideas and mechanics behind active
inference uh Bas role Basi and brain
hypothesis uh hidden States being
inferred from
observations uh action as a means of
trying to change the hidden State
through
transitions uh a lot of really kind of
foundational ideas uh towards
understanding active inference as well
as following along uh the low road
active inference starting from basian
can statistics as well as the hod active
inference following the uh principle of
free energy minimization so the second
half of the textbook I think is um it's
great for better understanding how to
more directly apply active inference so
chapter six a recipe for Designing
active inference models right off with
that kind of gives you a sense of what
the rest of the textbook is actually
going of potentially be about we'll be
learning how to design models uh chapter
seven and eight will be about uh putting
together discret and continuous time
models
respectively um so that's great for
people who want to um you know figure
out which kind of model they need for
their particular use case it's nice that
there are rather expansive chapters on
both types of those models chapter 9 uh
gets more into analysis so once you've
set up a an active inference simulation
uh it starts to discuss like how you can
actually interpret your results
um depending on your use case like how
you might set things up depending on
what your particular question or inquiry
is whenever you're setting up the
simulation and finally chapter 10 is a
nice uh wrap
that is maybe slightly out of place
compared to the rest of what I said
about uh the second half of the book but
it's uh it's good it's it's a rather
holistic kind of uh conclusion type
chapter both wrapping up the book
comparing active inference to a variety
of other disciplines and Fields like
control theory uh other social sciences
psychology uh reinforcement learning as
another approach these kinds of problems
and so on so uh just a quick overview on
chapter six again a recipe for Designing
active inference models uh the book the
uh the intro to this chapter uh friston
at all WR uh the challenge is not to
emulate the brain piece by piece but to
find the generative model that describes
the problem the brain's trying to solve
the model provides it so that refer two
is the model provides a complete
description of a system of interest and
the resulting Behavior inference and
neurodynamics can all be derived from a
model by minimizing free energy all
these ideas should be familiar from the
first half of the book but it's just
more clearly stating yes active
inference is heavily inherited from or
derived from uh different ways of
approaching computational Neuroscience
that said we are are not trying to
recreate you know um billions of
individual neurons and all of the kind
of crazy uh sparsely connected
architecture underlying say the human
brain or otherwise the empasis upon
developing generative models um you know
this kind of gets into the difference
between complexity and accuracy found in
uh any machine learning related problem
re enforcement learning problem so on so
again not trying to recreate the entire
brain uh just to where we can get things
accurate enough to where may start to
track and potentially could even be
fitted to empirical data um so whenever
uh we'll be introduced over time to more
Exemplar kind of models but we can adapt
the form of the models presented in this
textbook to our respective problem of
Interest we can change their form uh
should they be shallow or
hierarchical we can modify the variables
involved I.E uh the beliefs so what are
the states to infer what are the
observations that the agent receives
what are the actions or policies
available to the agent to
commit so from there there's it's really
just a four-step recipe um there are
entire discussions that could be had
about each step but in summary uh first
part first step is decide which system
are we modeling so what are the internal
versus external States what are the
sensory versus action States uh what is
the marov blanket of the system what
separates it out are there nested marov
blankets involved here those are all
basically questions and then step two of
the recipe is deciding what's the most
appropriate form for the generative
model like I mentioned earlier chapter
seven and chapter eight which
discuss uh discret versus continuous
time models so that's a big decision to
make uh potentially involving somewhat
different computations for minimizing
free energy underneath and one of them
were're uh working with categorical
probability distributions another one
we're working more with uh tailor series
and approximations
uh all of which are covered in the
textbook as well um we know that
hierarchical models versus shallow
models so hierarchical models May
operate at a slower time scale uh they
might uh basically involve learning
states are beliefs about states which
are then supplied back down to a lower
layer uh supplying prior for the lower
layer at the next time step or
otherwise um other questions involve
like the depth and of inference and of
planning how far into the future is the
agent uh inferring
States s questions of like expected free
energy come up so uh step three of the
recipe how do we set up the generative
model well we've already touched on it
but we decide on the model's variables
States observations
actions um in more detail that means
what are the obser ation modalities what
are the H State factors
overall um other things like how do we
Define the agent's habits or the prior
over its available policies um that's
kind of its its starting point for
deciding how to act uh what if we
exclude all the factors from the
equation and then finally which parts of
the model are fixed and which parts are
learned so certain parts might be
updated over time While others remain uh
static uh variables in the model and
finally step four how do we set up the
generative process uh the quick and easy
way of saying that is how do we Define
everything that is not the agent right
so so if it's the agent who commits
actions uh well those actions are then
going to technically be received by the
environment is one kind of figurative
way of looking at it so you need to
Define an environment that can take in
actions and then at each step whether in
discreete or continuous time output the
appropriate
observation um which will then be
received by the agent so that starts to
define a active inference action
perception Loop whatever setting things
up in code so um that's
in general the the sum of the chapter as
far as its four steps go there's plenty
of other things that are discussed along
the way and those four steps broken down
into uh smaller parts but um I think
that's a good enough overview for
now so I'll open up the floor for any
kinds of questions or just general
points of interest that people might
want to bring up to start a conversation
about and then I believe Daniel had some
some other thoughts regarding other
projects that are going on Institute uh
depending on what we have time
for I really enjoyed the uh the first
point the which system are we modeling
because as we design a system that's
going to have some specific environments
we're going to have some problem that we
may have imagined solving inside of it
which of course we're going to set up
our mark blanket and we're going to set
up our uh all of our situations but it
was interesting to me because it seems
like that's exactly what nature did
whenever it built like the brain and us
and stuff like that and it kind of put
it into perspective that the resolution
in which you're trying to solve is kind
of an arbitrary decision of variables
and where you arbitrarily decide to set
up your Markov blanket and it kind of
just set it into motion to me that oh
it's just Markov blankets all the way
down
yeah definitely I always anytime I I
start to reflect more on markup blankets
and what's been written about them I
just feel like we're in a world of uh of
Relativity um you know if I attempted to
model like myself say like What
Separates Me from what's around me um
well that said I'm composed of a series
of smaller markof blankets right I'm
composed a series of neurons and and and
other sort of processes that potentially
could be seen as as engaging in active
inference themselves or other
inferential processes so um yeah it's
it's so important to be able to delimit
if you're going to actually apply active
for instance set up a simulation like
what separates what is your system of
interest and what separates it from
those so-called
um otherwise we don't we don't know what
to do we don't know what to code and
um yeah we don't quite know what our
field of
studies yeah going off of that um I was
just reading some of RX environments
documentation earlier today
um and in in that case they actually
treat the environment or you can treat
the environment um like it's its own
agent in essence right it just doesn't
have a generative model behind it but
you know that's abstracted away um just
going off the Markov blankets all the
way
down yeah a lot of lot of great points
just on that last RX environments
piece it seems like part of what is
happening here is the generalization of
entity and then subtypes for like agent
and Niche and and that highlights what
but is also um like the Deep
symmetry between agent and
Niche with the same blanket one person's
send and receive as the other person's
receive and send in like a um Alice and
Bob communication
situation um and then also I mean there
there's there's a lot of
other um pieces to say like if you do
account for both directions across the
interface
like you have modeled what is at the
overlap of the agent in the niche so
that point choosing like
where which part belongs to which it's
like it's it's almost defined as the
interface belonging to both or
interfacing with both so that leads to a
lot of like the more
philosophical speculations and and
discussions around marov blanket
while while also just pragmatically
giving a very nuanced way to to talk
about like nested
systems absolutely I found it really I'm
sorry please go ahead I was just gonna
say practically just it eases
implementation a lot in the case of
Arts I found that really interesting and
I also wanted to ask guys I can't seem
to find it in the text embarrassingly
right now but whenever it was talking
about creating an agent that could walk
they were saying that you could have an
agent that embodies some generative
model that learns how to walk or you can
have legs that are built with the
Dynamics that in inherently don't have a
generative model but know how to walk
already know how to move in that
environment I found that to be really
interesting because it asked for me the
question of do we need the generative
model or do we just need a generative
model that has the generative model and
is that just a larger generative model
in of itself do you guys think about
that at all do you have any
thoughts one one relevant Direction
brought up earlier was that like the
choices about the model can always be
cast as a higher order modeling topic
and then another piece which I'll find
the link for will involve like this kind
of kind of embodied modeling like um
let's just say that the the elbow has
like a limited amount of lateral
Mobility or something like
that then if you're going to make a map
of that control theory setting there
might be two kinds of maps you can make
one that just simplifies no there's only
one um control variable and it has like
this limit and has this kind of like
frictions and things like that so over
Evolution that would come to embody
features that would make the first order
inference easier and
easier but that's not a guarantee of
just throwing some code on the page but
perhaps in in iterated evolution with
embodiment features of the model that in
silica would be purely needing
simulation would come
to like off Source or just be heris sixs
for what the embodiment was already
doing
yeah yeah I think it um comes back
to I I personally view it as like that
kind of
complexity accuracy trade-off question
again um one of my favorite uh
stimulations from active inference like
pieces of literature I've read I'm
personally interested in I guess what
would be called computational Psychiatry
and uh there's this nice paper
um that was put together to try and
simulate a classic tze Paradigm but
where the agent has like an effective
layer um all that is to say is that you
you take the t ma Paradigm you model a
mouse that has a hierarchical layer that
relates to emotion and see how the the
mouse's uh Behavior changes in the
teamas and and how it learns differently
and I
mean super cool and that said there are
dozens upon dozens of like model
architecture decisions that could have
been made there uh you've added an
entire aspect to the model and you could
have you know there could be so many
different things that you included in
this so why why just that one thing
suddenly is what the the question that
comes next rather than thinking know
this is a massive addition um so yeah I
it's just a lot of it is relativity I
think um classic way of going about
things is to design a model um do your
best and if you're designing it for a
particular use case uh see if it's
possible to try and fit that model to
empirical data through trying to you
know approximate behavior of a real um
living
organism or if you're trying to produce
something that you know has very high
optimal behavior for a particular task
Robotics and so on so just have to test
things
out this is that kind of one of the
examples it's like interesting how it's
it it is being pursued in duramorph and
other areas like this is this is a great
empirical
example through differential stiffness
and and control on differential
stiffness you have multi- joints
action with a falling weight with
differential stiffness and like
different tune tuning
stiffnesses but that's how posture
actually is
held rather than being like this wide
open control space like well my my
shoulder could be at any angle and my
elbow could be any angle with then then
there's going to be many control like
dimensions and
interactions um so another another um
topic to connect here um is an example
so the so in the uh summary Andrew gave
of step three how to set up the
generative model like what we associate
to what this is kind of a link to the o
inference ontology this is why we do
learn a generic system independent
scale-free
ontology even though our pragmatic
interest might be like in this specific
you know
X um here's taking basically what are
coming up in chapter 7 the discreete
time generative model as the a c d e o
s by listing those and then here it's at
three nested levels of modeling like the
pherone level most um feet on the ground
detecting phone perception that was kind
of what we got into in the infra ants
paper but then also we could think okay
well but the location switching and
that's kind of like the live stream 42
slam where the bottom level of the
nested model was the posture and the top
was location so you could have like a
warehouse robot that was like I want to
go like to location on the other side
but not have to do all the postural
modeling just having a slower transition
and then here it's like okay well and
task could have a
transition maybe it's just a binary
transition or that would be the
exploration how you model it but this is
the whole point about the system and
scale independent
ontology is that it's not the details of
the system which is why the ontology
doesn't have opinionation on like how
many nestmates should be in a colony or
how how rapidly should nurses shift the
forgers or back and forth like th those
are once you kind of see it very far in
the last mile of modeling that system of
interest and so it's totally described
by chapter
six why are we making this model what
are we actually choosing to model what
what kind of features are we taking as
data what Laten states are we going to
consider but the tabular form helps like
structure what otherwise can be a very
open-ended assembly process I guess this
is all it just clarifies it visually and
this is also good input for language
models with templates of other
code that's uh that's really fascinating
and it also kind of reminds me of a
problem that I heard of in self-driving
cars from a y a researcher named yon Le
and it was in his paper about uh jeppa
which they're asking how you create a
self-driving car that pays attention to
important things like other cars on the
road instead of just focusing on in
machine learning just classically
minimizing the loss because if you give
really really high definition cameras to
the
environment the car is going to start
looking where the most information
content is which is going to be at the
trees because those leaves moving there
is so much information going into there
but you're completely focusing on the
wrong things if you're looking at trees
whenever you're driving you might just
crash so what they have to do in
choosing the right sort of variables is
they found out they have to use these
hierarchical models which to try to cast
it into active inference terms they had
to create a hierarchy of a few different
Markov blankets however the actual
variables for the interfaces of the
inward blankets had to be kind of
coalescing inwards they had to be
abstractions you aren't allowed to use
the same variables again and again
because then you would find yourself in
a recursive problem where you keep
looking at the trees instead of focusing
on things like time scales or important
variables that occur down the road and
that's just something that I thought was
tangentially related to uh setting up
the generative model really interesting
stuff yeah great comments a few ways
that's played out so here's like one one
um fan favorite paper from
2021 that makes a three-level
phenomenological model so this is
commonly replicated and you're right
like a nested model does instantiate a
Markov blanket such that let's just say
that experience were
residing in the green but it doesn't
even matter about whether it's
phenomenological like awareness without
going too deep into that from the green
models
perspective the the the node that
interfaces with the orange is the marup
blanket and then also it's like that
actually goes further and so it is the
reason why although sometimes the
discussion is like what is the Markov
blanket quote around in agents but at
the same time
s13 is blanketed from s23 by b b is the
markof blanket intervening between two
time steps it's the transition operator
or a the this the observation to Hidden
State mapping like the partially
observable part is the Markov blanket
between the observable and the hidden
state so like the markovian time concept
past only influencing the future through
the present that's just the mark I'll
blanket through time so it's it's not a
statement or expression about H how any
agent or any Baye Network should be it's
actually so pervasive that the content
itself does like relatively limited work
because it's just a feature of any base
graph that's not fully connected is
going to have these markof blankets so
it it doesn't like distinguish certain
kinds of sparse connected Bas graphs
from others it it's just a feature that
is like basically is the sparsity of the
graph
that is absolutely fascinating I can't
wait to check that out thank you for
bringing it up yeah that that's a cool
one and then another another angle to to
like bring a more recent paper um than
than the textbook is
uh active data selection and information
seeking which was live stream 57 with
with friston and Par in the dot one and
then par joining in for do two um and
and great preparation work for
thezero like that is one of the things
that's super exciting about active
inference is there can be a lot of
useful tinkering along the low road and
like generating different architectures
for for nest and models and unified
approaches to to perception cognition
action
Etc here are some explicit ways to Value
the information with epistemic value and
that gets into talking about pragmatic
plus epistemic value but this is the
difference between reinforcement
learning and active inference in
reinforcement
learning epistemic
features must get projected down to or
onto or get lumped in with utility
reward because there's like a
uni ranking that different policies are
getting ranked against and then policies
are selected or sampled from that
utility basis and so there's all kinds
of tricks like well give a bonus for
learning information but that would also
come to exactly the same question which
is how should information be valued and
then like a sort of first pass approach
like just have high you know frame rate
differencing which is the origins of
predictive coding where the frame rate
differencing is giving High information
content that's where you would want to
focus but that is like a rapidly moving
tree like you brought up like it could
have high frame rate differencing but it
wouldn't reduce uncertainty about is
there a tree there and so active data
selection and considering epistemic
value
explicitly helps give exact and
composable epistemic values for
generative models and gives like a
playground slash space where epistemic
and pragmatic value are not the same as
each other
and yet they can be balanced so there is
the parametric balancing like if if it's
an explore exploit Tas or multi-arm
Bandit it's not just like making the
situation is going to guarantee that you
have resolved the
tradeoff even though language is kind of
used to that extent or effect in the
textbook that this like dissolves the
explore exploit trade-off whereas a
slightly more toned down approach that
does doesn't like promise a given result
is it sets up the setting where explore
exploit can be compared without
collapsing like the explore component to
some higher order exploitation
problem just a quick comment on that
that um I've personally been uh putting
together a
three-hour tutorial on applying active
inference I'll actually be uh presenting
it in a couple days uh International
Conference on computational social
sciences and
Philadelphia a couple days from now and
I I've you know one of the strongest
points of interest for social scientists
is this uh explore exploit you know
dilemma and I just I think one of the
most interesting points about is it can
almost be viewed as like both things are
being included in roughly the same
optimization problem and I I think that
the textbook is coming out of a context
where where this active inference is
being heavily compared to reinforcement
learning is a potential alternative way
of going about producing these
models um and exploration and
exploitation do tend to be treated
separately where you need like an
additional set of rules uh for defining
like what what is it that defines
exploratory behavior for an agent versus
exploitative and it seen I think is just
introducing additional
assumptions uh into a reinforcement
learning model in order to differentiate
those whereas with active inference
there's this sort of quote unquote
natural balancing between the two but
also agreed that like yes now in the
same optimization problem they're both
included in U Computing expected free
energy for an active inference agent but
it doesn't necessarily mean the agent is
always going to find some theoretical
correct amount of exploratory value or
Tim value in particular action versus
pragmatic there could be n there could
be zero it could always think like oh if
I do this or this I'm never going to
learn anything so I might as well just
go for the goal so to speak um but yeah
sorry I've just been thinking about that
a lot while uh putting this together but
maybe that's useful for for someone
thinking about
it yeah where that's shown most uh
clearly in analytically figure
26 here's expected free energy it's a
functional on Pi which is like a vector
of policy priors that sums to one and
then actions are either drawn from the
top or the most likely or sampled from
PI with either a straight sampling on Pi
or you can have a temperature on action
so sample from a more blurred out P or a
more sharpened Pi what G does in these
models expected for energy is it takes a
policy prior prior to the update and
then updates it into a policy posterior
so it's sharpening policies according to
pragmatic plus epistemic value both
explicitly designed so it has these
elements 1 2 3 4 five but really it's
two major terms the first one here is
pragmatic value so if you only have
pragmatic value only
utility maximization that is expected
utility and basian decision Theory so
this does not Encompass there to be
learning or at a higher level it
reflects a setting where a modeler has
given a utilitarian value to a learning
event so in practice that might pursue
learning like learning likeed Behavior
but it it did so by saying well uh
getting a problem right is worth one but
learning how to do it is worth two so
then pursue as many points as you can
and then it starts learning capacities
or something or you can have 2 three
four five included and drop the price
magmatic value this is like the novelty
search
Infomax because it it kind of has
implicitly a flat utility distribution
so
then decisions are weighted only
according to the amount of information
that they provide which is
operationalized as the K Divergence
double line
between hidden States X Tilda
with pi either way and Y tlda is the
sequence of observations so if the
sequence of observations was expected to
contribute nothing to beliefs about
extra time this K Divergence would be
zero whereas if yelda is anticipated to
change beliefs on X through time that
has a high KL Divergence so it's the
Pure epistemic Element the pure
pragmatic element is about alignment of
observ future observations through time
with preferences the prior Distribution
on
observations and then those two
pragmatic and epistemic imperatives come
together in expected free energy and
then there's the degree of freedom of
how those are balanced and then choices
about how would you dynamically allocate
the balance so it's not solved in
practice however analytically it's
pretty clear
well another fun direction to to at
least
um begin here is like we're two years
after publication of the book and one of
the biggest changes in
the active inference environment has
been RX and fur um several of us are are
working on this and
[Music]
um we
have uh figure 1.2 with with help from
some of the bias
lab I I'll put this in the chat and and
we'll see but the the goal of this kind
of um shared project between the ARX and
forur project and textbook group the
goal is to have code for every setting
and figure in the textbook
and that would be
um we can do it in a few different repos
we can have uh copies in uh notebooks so
it can just be
run
uh there's a table of all RX and fur
examples so here's the reactive base
these are 23 examples from a
documentation here's kobus eser Housen
here's eight examples from his is
website learnable
Loop then here's figure
1.2 so here's a
notebook that will
install you click run runtime run all
first time it hits the first block it's
going to install Julia then it'll say
reload the page that brings you into the
Julia kernel then runtime run all again
second time through it installs it runs
the tests that confirm that Julia is
installed and then it installs the
packages that are relevant for RX and
fur then here is is a great example
of without even going into RX and verse
performance engineering or like
computational benefits just focusing on
the textbook group possibilities and and
educational possibilities
here we have figure 2.1 so it's like the
Frog of the apple is either jumping out
of the hand or not and then we have an
agent who has priors about the
prevalence of frogs and apples in the
world and then they update what they
believe they're actually holding on to
or did did hold on to based upon the
observation either a jump or not so the
at model
Block in RX and fur is like the not to
crack this is the
closest not not the closest it could
ever be but this is the closest we've
ever seen the concordance between the
equations that analytically Define a
generative model and the code to do so
and so that also captures the biggest
difference with RX and fur from a design
perspective overall which is in PDP and
in in mat laab there's a procedural
definition of for example the agents
interfacing with the environment like
for a new observation then this happens
that kicks off this calculate this
update that move this to here and so it
gives a script like flow that's a
manable to explicit looping over like
elements of planning or elements of of
of across multiple agents then there's a
lot of degrees of freedom with like okay
but then you know should agent one go
first every time step or how how do we
deal with that ARX infer replaces that
with a declarative programming style so
here this is the base graph as declared
and it's basically what you see is what
you get with the types of
distributions and they could be
parameterized here directly or it could
be parameterized elsewhere and then the
inference is also as direct as you can
get it's basically just calling that
base graph as declared doing some stuff
under the hood that we can explore more
and then letting that graph in its
definition be uncoupled from the actual
message passing like Logistics of
information flow between the nodes
that's the part that goes under the hood
now with RX and fur so it opens up this
possibility
where the app model specifications of
the generative model look a lot like the
equations and like the minimal way to
describe a
situation without this extra control
flow of which nodes are updated in what
order however that has to be
supplemented in so that's a lot of the
ongoing work is like what are the syntax
and possibilities for these app model
functions what else needs to come into
play to to have
interpretability and and kind of like
getting it run without any errors also
but getting it working in a in a way
that seems to function and maybe even
Leverage The reactive message passing
part and then also what that would mean
is not just for like different languages
and programming backgrounds and
everything but then in this par textbook
group there would be a really clear path
from like here's figure or 2.1 and now
here's how you could continue to learn
more about RX and fur and that would
take one like all the way to the Horizon
of modeling it in advanced settings so
that's a clear pathway whereas the 2022
textbook otherwise the appendix doesn't
fully reproduce all the figures it's
also in mat
lab so then it's like well you're out of
for with whether you recommend or go to
study these examples code in more detail
or kind of start on a fresh late with
like PDP which is probably what in
earlier cohorts we discussed a
lot but now there's kind of a tiebreaker
with RX and fur and the missing artifact
that we could greatly benefit from would
be the
one-time finite basically task of making
RX and for models and notebooks for the
textbook group
a and in doing so making the
accessory um kind of Explorations and
having the conversations that are like
the questions in chapter
six and so just kind
of then then we like we
have like a tinkering format in
common and one that we can run in
notebooks and one that looks largely
like the equations
kind of written out more in uh
programming form so not not not to go
too too much on this but and and this
notebook also contains some
extraneous
um
information but if we
can Bridge it with RX and fur and the
textbook group It'll like really give a
great connection between the education
onramps and the
application that that is also like an
open source
framework yeah I would I would second
that um I think that'd be super cool um
I've personally been using uh PDP for
that tutorial I I mentioned earlier um
and I mean the developers of it are are
great um you know I've been talking with
him personally a little bit um but that
said yeah I've seen a lot of the
benefits of RX andur and hope to get
back into the RX andur group uh seems
like really exciting work and finally to
bring it back um I think especially for
part two of the book at for anyone
anyone in the textbook groups coming in
cohorts looking to actually design
active inference models themselves like
this chapter
like what how do we Define a system of
Interest how do we
actually code that is the the additional
question that isn't necessarily answered
uh in the chapters that we're reading
here right it's kind of implied in that
you know it's uh the authors of the
textbook do use mat lab as you mentioned
Daniel and so it's kind of as well as
the the the appendix does include like
some uh some figures of direct matlb
code constructing the a matrices and so
on and PP
but yeah being able to supplement the
textbook group with RX in for code which
is also from my perspective the most up
to-date way of maybe even doing active
inference I think I think that would be
incredibly exciting and I think it would
also Supply people with one a great
Learning Resource like oh this is how
you do this and then two uh IT Supplies
a bunch of potential templates that
people could download and modify for
their own personal experiences um in the
sense that you know part of active
inference is that we don't just learn by
changing our perception we learn by
changing the world so um making these
kind of templates available for people
for them to try and test out their ideas
themselves I think kind of fulfills the
other half of the equation of maybe how
to learn how to apply
place so really exciting
stuff yeah I just wanted to Second the
value of templates for ARX and fur in
that different models can be
hierarchically
composed um along with each other so
yeah once one is specified has a lot
going
forward yeah getting some really clear
documented
examples and and getting the
visualization functionalities and then
the examples of what those motifs look
like building libraries that can then be
referenced by llms for code generation
to um building some more methods for
like the meta programming and and the
interpretability moving in and out of
other formats like there there's a lot
of exciting ways to go um and chapter
six is going to be kind of there
meeting point because that's where we
will that's that's the beginning of the
modeling process again with the
selection of the system of Interest
which is kind of this like open ended
stage but then following that it starts
to progressively
specify and eventually in a way
constrain the output of just a final
generative
model so that that Dem mystifies I think
a lot of the
process and and will will like create
lower
friction paths to get from like a given
data set
to something that's that's doing
something
useful I remember one discussion from
from many cohorts ago um of like then
there's the pr Matic value of making the
generative model which would be like
okay I'm making air conditioning and so
I prefer it to be like low energy so
then I need to make a working model so
that it works and then there's also the
epistemic value like people learning
about active inference learning about
thems learning about each other um like
learning about what is possible that
it's like it never even needs to reach
the final artifact although that final
artifact might also provide epistemic
value separate from its pragmatic value
too so it's like not a worthless process
e even if it um and and and how hard
different stages are it's super system
dependent and that Frontier is very
rapidly moving
too so it's it's quite different than it
was like one or two or three years ago
so I would expect it to be also multiple
fold to orders of magnitude easier in
one two three
years so it's just sort of
like jumping in while you can and and
then your own experiences and Records
will help calibrate and show where
things actually are shifting and
how easy or hard they
are okay I do want to quickly add
because I know we about out of time but
uh much much earlier uh during
introductions uh someone I think Zach
had mentioned an interest in
interpretability of of models and I
would love to see in RX for
like I'm saying this partially because
of just ignorance of of what people have
tried so far but of course people are
minimizing free energy but maybe a
little bit of emphasis on like different
of helper functions that can maybe pull
out you know for a given time step for
example what was the expected
Information Gain um of you know choosing
a particular action or policy for the
agent like basically having functions
that help you pull out like well here's
the parts of this that are
comprehensible right um for me I'm
putting together this tutorial for
social scientists it's like well if we
can't extract it any interesting or
useful insights from these models then
why are we memorizing all of this
relatively complex math why are we
spending our our time doing that and so
like for me it's like oh well you can
you know make say 30 agents and now you
can have them do things that lead to
emerging behaviors but now you can
actually peer into you know if if
they're learning their likelihood models
now you can look at their particular
beliefs and how they change over time
and consider those to be something like
cognitive metrics that we can actually
interpret like we can interpret them
mathematically we understand how they
work but we also can see how they impact
Behavior Uh model performance and
Longevity um and and so on so yeah it'd
be super cool to to just make sure with
all these nice uh technical advancements
that are being made with with Julian ARS
Ander to to also supplement that with
with you know interpretability and and
having that is a ready Resource as
well yeah no absolutely oh sorry after
you oh yeah I was I was just gonna say I
I think today it's it's probably quite
limited but arxon for debug mode does
show like messages being passed it's
most useful to my understanding
recommended
um for when you're unable to optimize
the the graph right you're not
converging on on a solution you're just
running forever um usually you're
running some sort of intractable problem
I don't know how much that helps with
interpretability I don't understand
message fasing super well um and I I
just swed a a talk from Demitri bagv
earlier today it's link to the AR for
the engineering Discord Channel um he
talks about how it took him years to
understand message passing so there's
that um the other thing that I would I
don't think this functionality exists
but I would possibly look forward to
maybe understanding these models ESP as
they growing complexity um is sort of
like loss of function research on them
so like disabling or removing parts of
the subgraph um because these are
all all of the message passing happens
locally it's just in between two nodes
um so you can you know the example
that's commonly used is like you could
lose a sensor that's feeding into the
model um and it would still continue to
work with it's just optimizing without
that um so yeah maybe that that would be
kind of an interesting approach as
well I'll try to give the shortest
possible message passing that this this
is a super interesting paper I hope we
can like understand these different
approximations but but leaving that for
a second the
2017 paper with with Bert here's the key
figure this is connecting figure 4.3
discreet time generative model this is a
base graph nodes are the random
variables edges are the causal
relationships in the 40 Factor graph the
nodes and edges are flipped so that the
node are like combiners or functions of
where different variables which which
are on the edges come from there's as as
they showed there's like a onetoone
mapping between a base graph and a
forign factor graph so they can contain
the exact same information what you gain
though with a factor graph is this like
Logistics or scheduling order so it
allows you to like turn the crank ahead
one step and to say that's going to take
these 22 messages in this exact order
what those messages are there's a lot of
different like payloads they can contain
but what it lets the whole graph do is
do one descent on a variational free
energy landscape for example it could
probably also do other things so in 2017
they were like we're already making
these Bas graphs here's a logistically
deterministic scheduler that'll let us
crank even on a large base graph let us
crank the whole thing ahead one time
step at a time that that's message
passing or variational message passing
the difference with reactive and what
Demitri I think brought in with the
rocket is it uncouples the update
frequencies from different parts of the
graph so instead of having to turn the
whole crank and run this deterministic
schedule of every single thing you can
have the reactive like just in time
sending and receiving I believe that
opens up some other things that need to
be specified like how the logistics are
but it seems like those are just
conventions and actually the reactivity
means that like the graph doesn't have a
order or Tempo per
se but it's like figuring out all those
things are some of the most important
things right and this kind of reactivity
um I I've wondered like the connection
between message passing here and message
passing in the case of uh like
multi or or distributed
computing um it seems like with the
reactivity you're getting possibly very
close to that I don't know if it's
something that's been discussed
much that's super interesting I think
it's probably almost totally unexplored
with a multi-threading there's
multi-threading and concurrent uh
programming as like a multi-agent
situation right I don't know if how like
if those kinds of moves have been
brought into like possible multi-cpu or
GPU RX and
fur yeah yeah I don't I I don't know
either it's it's very interesting the
parallel there it seems yeah I'd love to
learn more about it but I I also know
not too much about distributive
Computing so maybe something to explore
cool well this is a fun uh sort of
reentry into six like also we'll have
the three-week Rhythm so
let's in the third weeks Let's either
work on a textbook example
Andor annotating code from from CIS or
the examples but let let let's go into
RX and fur and um and curate the
questions along way and make the
notebooks
Etc possibly we could record these
sessions but we'll see if it's just as
more like an application
Workshop um I think this will be really
fun though and help G give like kind of
a textbook part two plus because after
having done and then also then we leave
these kind of like perhaps multiple
Workshop templates for cohort 7 going
through the second half half and then
that would be like a jumping off point
for okay then you finished that but
you're already pretty familiar with
artics and Fur by the end of the
textbook
group because the application oriented
part of the book gives templates and
examples so still many people SL all
people will be learning code and Julia
and RX and
fur but then that's where we can also
connect to using llms for code
explanations and all this other
stuff so thank you Andrew thank you John
and
Zach thank you guys so much Daniel I'm
excited to read those papers and check
out our I'll talk to you guys soon see
you bye